Guide to the Lyman A. Spalding papers, 1811-1864 (bulk)
Spalding, Lyman A. papers, 1811-1864 (bulk)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Lyman A. Spalding Papers, 1811-1864 (bulk)
522
Lyman A. Spalding
.4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, financial records, publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Contains correspondence, manuscripts, records, and publications related to the career of Lyman A. Spalding, a nineteenth-century Quaker merchant and abolitionist who lived in upstate New York. He was co-editor of the newspaper Plain Truth and established the newspaper Priestcraft Exposed and Primitive Christianity Defended.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Lyman A. Spalding was a Quaker merchant involved in manufacturing and banking in New York State and the Midwest, and real estate and lumbering in Michigan Territory early in the 19th century. He was an active member in the abolition movement, edited the Plain Truth, and established the newspaper Priestcraft Exposed and Primitive Christianity Defended.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
This collection, which throws light on the intellectual history of Western New York and on the anti-slavery movement in the North (1822-36), includes letters to Spalding relating to his mercantile business in Canandaigua, Ontario County (1817-23) and in Lockport, Niagara County (1823-50); to his manufacture of agricultural implements in Lockport (1840s); to merchandising in New York and the Midwest (1820-40); to banking in Rochester and New York (1819-24); and to labor, land, and lumbering in Michigan Territory (1817-35). Included are letters from Thomas B. Barnum of Canandaigua (1823-24), editor of the Ontario Freeman (a Canandaigua, N.Y. newspaper) and co-editor with Spalding of Plain Truth; letters from Elisha Dean of Rochester (1829-30) on local affairs, court cases, and the election of 1830; letters from Holmes Hutchinson, surveyor, on personal affairs, and on surveys in New England on the Erie and other canals; letters from Elihu Francis Marshall, who was the city treasurer of Rochester, a reformer, journalist, printer, and publisher, on personal affairs, business, banking, politics, and churches in Rochester, and satirizing the "Missionary spirit"; a letter (1826) describing missionary activities in the Society Islands; letters from Harvey Newcomb of Rochester (1820s) on politics, business, and the press. Many of the letters of the 1820s comment on the political and economic agitation over the construction and functioning of the Erie and other canals.
Also included are letters relating to the establishment by Spalding of the newspaper Priestcraft Exposed and Primitive Christianity Defended, the manuscript editorials and articles for the first issue, and other letters concerning its relationship to the Plain Truth; three letters to Spalding from Benjamin Lundy (1835-36) relating to his plan to establish a colony in Mexico, to the "Mexican Insurrection" and to the intention of Lydia Maria Francis Child to settle in the colony, and mentioning John Quincy Adams's purchase for distribution of 150 Texas pamphlets; a plea by Oliver Wetmore of Utica, secretary of the NYSSAS, to the presidents of local abolitionist groups (of which Spalding was one) to subsidize the Standard Democrat of Utica as an abolitionist newspaper; and copies of the Plain Truth.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Spalding, Lyman A.; Barnum, Thomas B.; Child, Lydia Maria Francis, 1802-1880.; Dean, Elisha.; Hutchinson, Holmes.; Lundy, Benjamin, 1789-1839.; Marshall, Elihu F.; Newcomb, Harvey, 1803-1863.; Wetmore, Oliver.
Titles:
Ontario freeman.; Plain truth.; Priestcraft exposed.
Subjects:
Agricultural machinery industry.; Banks and banking.; Canals--New York (State); Elections--New York (State); Journalism--New York (State); Journalism--New York (State)--Canandaigua.; Journalism, Religious.; Working class--Michigan.; Labor--Michigan.; Merchandising.; Missions--French Polynesia--Society Islands.; Anti-slavery movements.; Newspapers.; Politics, Practical.; Transportion--New York (State); Quakers.; Abolitionists.; Journalists.; Merchants.; Missionaries.
Places:
Canandaigua (N.Y.)--Commerce.; Erie Canal (N.Y.); Lockport (N.Y.)--Commerce.; Mexico--Politics and government.; Michigan--Commerce.; New York (State)--Politics and government.; Rochester (N.Y.)--Commerce.; Rochester (N.Y.)--Politics and government.; Rochester (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Society Islands (French Polynesia)--Religious life and customs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, 1811-1816 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Jan.-May 1820 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, July-Dec. 1820 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, Jan.-June 1822 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, July-Dec. 1822 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, Jan.-Mar. 1823 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, May-Dec. 1823 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, Jan.-June 1824 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, July-Dec. 1824 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1825-1826 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1827-1828 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1829-1830 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1831-1832 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1833-1834 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, Jan.-Mar. 1835 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, Apr.-Nov. 1835 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1837-1839 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1840-1844 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1845-1850, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Legal documents, 1828-1846 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Manuscripts [copies?] on various topics, 1819-1828 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Publication: "Reflections on the War of 1812 and Early Life in Western New York," by Spalding, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Accounts, 1819, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Receipts, inventory, etc., 1839, 1850, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Miscellany (Box 1, Folder 31)